Guide to the Jacques Barzun Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XIII: 1986-87 Gift
  - Columbia University--Personal correspondence, 1982-86 (Box 283)
  - Cornelia Street Theatre, 1976 (Box 284)
  - Council for Basic Education (CBE) (1), 1976 (Box 284)
  - Council for Basic Education (CBE) (2), 1983-86 (Box 284)
  - Council for Basic Education (CBE): Volume of letters of appreciation to JB, 1986 (Box 284)
  - Critic: Appeals, 1981-January 86 (Box 285)
  - Critic: General, 1980-85 (Box 285)
  - Dallas Institute of Humanities and Culture, 1980-85 (Box 285)
  - Detective fiction--General correspondence, 1975-86 (Box 285)
  - Educational criticism, 1982-86 (Box 285)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1983-84 (Box 285)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1985-86 (Box 285)
  - Foreign rights, 1968-76 (Box 285)
  - Foundation for Economic Development, 1969-83 (Box 285)
  - Garland Publishing, 1978-83 (Box 285)
  - Goodman. Jonathan: correspondence, 1973-82 (Box 286)
  - "History--The Muse and Her Doctors" (article), 1971-74 (Box 286)
  - Interviews with JB, 1981-86 (Box 286)
  - Invitations: Misc., 1979-82 (Box 286)
  - Invitations: Misc., 1983-86 (Box 286)
  - Language: Letters about, 1979-86 (Box 286)
  - Lectures: Accepted, 1982 (Box 287)
  - Lectures: Accepted (1), 1983-85 (Box 287)
  - Lectures: Accepted (2), 1983-85 (Box 287)
  - Lectures: Comments on, 1982-May 85 (Box 287)
  - Lectures: Declined, 1982-September 85 (Box 287)
  - Lectures: Possible, 1983-85 (Box 287)
  - Library of Congress, 1977-85 (Box 288)
  - The London Athenaeum, 1982-86 (Box 288)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1977-86 (Box 288)
  - Miscellany re: Richard Ellman, Henry Kissinger. 1969 72 (Box 288)
  - Music: General correspondence, 1967-86 (Box 288)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1972-85 (Box 288)
  - New York Society Library (1), 1981-86 (Box 288)
  - New York Society Library (2), 1981-86 (Box 288)
  - New York Society Library Book Committee, 1982-86 (Box 288)
  - Nineteenth century music, 1976-81 (Box 289)
  - Original outlines for published works, undated (Box 289)
  - Paideia: Files (1), 1982-84 (Box 289)
  - Paideia: Files (2), 1982-84 (Box 289)
  - Paideia: Files, 1985-86 (Box 289)
  - Paideia: Initial proposal, 1978 (Box 289)
  - Peabody Institute, Baltimore (1), 1983-85 (Box 290)
  - Peabody Institute. Baltimore (2), 1983-85 (Box 290)
  - Permissions, 1980-83 (Box 290)
  - Permissions, 1984-86 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: A-Z, 1958-79 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: Ashby. Sir Eric, 1970-72 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: Boardman. Harry, 1970-79 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: Canfield, Cass, 1967-76 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: Caplow, Ted, 1969-84 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: Davis, Colin, 1967-76 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: St. John-Stevas, Norman, 1968-75 (Box 290)
  - Personal correspondence: A-C, 1979-82 (Box 291)
  - Personal correspondence: D-G, 1979-82 (Box 291)
  - Personal correspondence: H-K, 1979-82 (Box 291)
  - Personal correspondence: L-R, 1979-82 (Box 291)
  - Personal correspondence: S-Z, 1979-82 (Box 291)
  - Personal correspondence: misc., 1983-85 (Box 292)
  - Personal correspondence: A, 1983-85 (Box 292)
  - Personal correspondence: B, 1983-85 (Box 292)
  - Personal correspondence: C, 1983-85 (Box 292)
  - Personal correspondence: D, 1983-85 (Box 292)
  - Personal correspondence: E, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: F, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: G, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: H-J, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: Jacobsen. Herbert, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: K, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: L, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: Mc, 1983-85 (Box 293)
  - Personal correspondence: H, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: N, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: O, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: P, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: Q, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: R, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence; S, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: T, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: V, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal correspondence: W-Z, 1983-85 (Box 294)
  - Personal notices: JB (1), 1985-86 (Box 295)
  - Personal notices: JB (2), 1956-82 (Box 295)
  - Personal notices: JB (3), 1981-86 (Box 295)
  - Personal notices: JB (4), undated (Box 295)
  - Plays performed, 1967-71 (Box 295)
  - Plays published, 1970-74 (Box 295)
  - Poetry declined, 1916-84 (Box 295)
  - Publishing: Articles and general correspondence, 1982-86 (Box 295)
  - Radio and TV programs, 1978-84 (Box 295)
  - Recommendations A-B, 1976-86 (Box 296)
  - Recommendations C-F, 1976-86 (Box 296)
  - Recommendations G-H, 1976-86 (Box 296)
  - Recommendations I-H, 1976-86 (Box 296)
  - Recommendations N-R, 1976-86 (Box 296)
  - Recommendations S-Z, 1976-86 (Box 296)
  - Releases on J13, 1973-84 (Box 297)
  - Royalty statements (alphabetical by publisher):
    - A-F, 1980-86 (Box 297)
    - G-Harc, 1980-86 (Box 297)
    - Harp-Z, 1980-86 (Box 297)
  - Butler (pamphlet), 1963-72 (Box 297)
  - Scribner's: Misc. correspondence, 1975-80 (Box 297)
  - Scribner's Editorial Files 1975-86:
    - Correspondence: A, 1976-84 (Box 298)
    - Atlas of Cultural History, 1975-76 (Box 298)
    - Correspondence: B (1), 1976-85 (Box 298)
    - Correspondence: B (2), 1976-85 (Box 298)
    - Books in preparation, 1977-84 (Box 298)
    - Boritt, Gabor--Lincoln project and Scribner Presidents reference history, 1982-84 (Box 298)
    - British writers, 1975-85 (Box 299)
    - Correspondence: C, 1975-85 (Box 299)
    - Continental writers, 1978-85 (Box 299)
    - Crime Novel Prize, 1981-82 (Box 299)
    - Correspondence: D., 1975-85 (Box 299)
    - David and Charles Holding. Ltd., 1978 (Box 299)
    - Correspondence: E, 1976-86 (Box 299)
    - Correspondence: F., 1975-84 (Box 300)
    - Correspondence: G., 1976-85 (Box 300)
    - Goodman. Jonathan, 1976-84 (Box 300)
    - Correspondence: H., 1975-85 (Box 300)
    - Haagensen. Cushman (Breast Cancer), 1982-84 (Box 300)
    - Hastings, Mrs. J.A. (Frederika Blair)--Isadora Duncan, 1978 (Box 300)
    - Historical Background of English Literature, 1975-76 (Box 300)
    - History of Western Civilization, 1980-81 (Box 300)
    - Correspondence: I-J, 1975-86 (Box 300)
    - In-house memos, 1975-86 (Box 301)
    - Correspondence: K, 1975-86 (Box 301)
    - Correspondence: L, 1975-86 (Box 301)
    - Correspondence: M (1), 1975-86 (Box 301)
    - Correspondence: H (2), 1975-86 (Box 301)
    - Mystery writers, 1975-86 (Box 301)
    - Correspondence: N-O, 1975-84 (Box 302)
    - Correspondence: P-Q, 1975-86 (Box 302)
    - Morris Philipson, 1975-82 (Box 302)
    - Personnel, 1978-82 (Box 302)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (1): general correspondence (Box 302)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (2): manuscripts and correspondence (Box 302)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (3): notes and correspondence, 1983 (Box 302)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (4): Annexes de A-N inclus., undated (Box 303)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (5): En Quatorze Tableaux: L'Action De Pierre Laval Et La Vie De La France De, 1940-1944 undated (Box 303)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (6): photocopied material. Correspondence, 1982 (Box 303)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (7): correspondence, printed, and photocopied material, 1982-83 (Box 303)
    - Pierre Laval (Rene de Chambrun) (8): notices and reviews 1983 (Box 303)
    - Correspondence: R 1975-85 (Box 303)
    - Ryan, Helen Clark, 1978-82 (Box 303)
    - Correspondence: S (1), 1975-86 (Box 304)
    - Correspondence: S (2), 1975-86 (Box 304)
    - Scribner-Bantam Dictionary, 1976-78 (Box 304)
    - Snow, C. P., 1975-80 (Box 304)
    - Correspondence: T, 1975-86 (Box 304)
    - Tremain, Ruth:Dictionary of Animals, 1979-82 (Box 304)
    - Nancy Toff: The Flute Book, 1980-86 (Box 304)
    - Correspondence: U-V, 1975-84 (Box 304)
    - Correspondence: W, 1975-85 (Box 304)
    - William James Lectures (Eugene Taylor), 1980-84 (Box 304)
    - Correspondence: X-Z, 1977-85 (Box 304)
  - Shaw, George Bernard: General correspondence, 1939-79 (Box 304)
  - Speeches, 1974 (Box 305)
  - Speeches, 1975 (Box 305)
  - Speeches, 1976 (Box 305)
  - Speeches, 1977 (Box 306)
  - Speeches, 1978 (Box 306)
  - Speeches, 1979 (Box 306)
  - Speeches, 1980 (Box 307)
  - Speeches, 1981 (Box 307)
  - Speeches, 1982 (Box 307)
  - Speeches, 1983 (Box 307)
  - Speeches, 1984 (Box 307)
  - Speeches, 1985 (Box 307)
  - Translation: general correspondence, 1970-77 (Box 308)
  - Lionel and Diana Trilling, 1979-85 (Box 308)
  - Lionel Trilling: comments on JB's Trilling memoir, 1976-80 (Box 308)
  - Lionel Trilling: Lionel Trilling file (1), 1975-79 (Box 308)
  - Lionel Trilling: Lionel Trilling file (2), 1975-85 (Box 308)
  - Lionel Trilling: Lionel Trilling Seminars, 1982-87 (Box 308)
  - Lionel Trilling: Reviews and publicity 1975-86 (Box 308)
  - Typescripts, through 1943 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1944-45 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1946-50 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1951-54 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1955 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1956 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1957-58 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1959 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1960-61 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1962 (Box 309)
  - Typescripts, 1963 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts, 1964-65 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts, 1966-67 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts, 1968-69 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts (1), 1970-71 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts (2), 1970-71 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts, 1972-73 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts (1), 1974-75 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts (2), 1974-75 (Box 310)
  - Typescripts (1), 1975-76 (Box 311)
  - Typescripts (2), 1975-76 (Box 311)
  - Typescripts (1), 1977 (Box 311)
  - Typescripts (2), 1977 (Box 311)
  - Typescripts, 1978 (Box 312)
  - Typescripts, 1979 (Box 312)
  - Typescripts (1), 1980 (Box 312)
  - Typescripts (2), 1980 (Box 312)
  - Typescripts, 1981 (Box 313)
  - Typescripts (1), 1982 (Box 313)
  - Typescripts (2), 1982 (Box 313)
  - Typescripts (3), 1982 (Box 313)
  - Typescripts (1), 1983 (Box 314)
  - Typescripts (2), 1983 (Box 314)
  - Typescripts (1), 1984 (Box 314)
  - Typescripts (2), 1984 (Box 314)
  - Typescripts (1), 1985 (Box 315)
  - Typescripts (2), 1985 (Box 315)
  - University of Buckingham, 1977-86 (Box 315)
  - University of Chicago Press/Harris Philipson, 1975-86 (Box 315)
  - University of North Carolina Library, 1975-85 (Box 315)
  - Book files: Book files are divided into five categories:
    A. Books: General files
    B. Books: Books by Barzun
    C. Books: With contributions by Barzun
    D. Edited by Barzun
    E. Books: Translations by Barzun.
    All files include correspondence, manuscripts. and related materials.
  - A. Books: General files:
    - General publicity on books by JB (1), 1977 (Box 316)
    - General publicity on books by JB (2), 1977-85 (Box 316)
    - Invitations to write a textbook, 1930-61 (Box 316)
    - James. William: Correspondence related to James, 1936-72 (Box 316)
    - Suggested books: Correspondence, 1954-76 (Box 316)
  - B. Books: Books by Barzun
    - The American University, 1968-86 (Box 317)
    - Berlioz and the Romantic Century: English, French, and paperback editions, 1967-86 (Box 317)
    - Berlioz and the Romantic Century: Possible reprint, 1981 (Box 317)
    - Classic, Romantic and Modern, 1959-1977 (Box 317)
    - Clio and the Doctors: Correspondence, 72-85 (Box 317)
    - Clio and the Doctors: Material and reviews, 75-77 (Box 317)
    - Critical Questions, 1972-86 (Box 318)
    - Darwin. Marx and Wagner, 1948-86 (Box 318)
    - Darwin, Marx and Wagner, revised edition 1979-86 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 1960-73 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: Outline, undated (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: Introduction: "Critical Inquiry", 1975 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art. 2nd. Series: "The Life and Death of Modernism", 1976 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Oscar Wilde’s Permanent Place", 1964 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "The Mind of Diderot," 1956-73 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "On and On With Thomas Mann", 1948 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Red Chartreuse", 1962 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Why Opera", 1967 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Art in Government and University", 1965 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "De Mortuis", undated (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Zola and the Coal Strike", 1962 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "The Novel Turns Tale", undated (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Re-reading Santayana", 1954 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "Please, Doctor. May Historians Use WordsÀ" 1968 (Box 318)
    - The Energies of Art, 2nd. Series: "The Other Decalogue", undated (Box 318)
    - God’s Country and Mine, 1957-86 (Box 319)
    - The House of Intellect: Correspondence, 1961-86 (Box 319)
    - The House of Intellect II: Correspondence, 1981 (Box 319)
    - The Modern Researcher, 1970-83 (Box 319)
    - The Modern Researcher, 1984-85 (Box 319)
    - The Modern Researcher, 3rd. Edition, 1975-82 (Box 319)
    - The Modern Researcher, 3rd. Edition: Proofs, memos, 1976-77 (Box 319)
    - Of Human Freedom, 1969-80 (Box 320)
    - Pragmatism Revisited, 1957-75 (Box 320)
    - On Writing. Editing and Publishing, 1972-86 (Box 320)
    - Race. A Study in Superstition, 1954-82 (Box 320)
    - Science. the Glorious Entertainment, 1964-75 (Box 320)
    - Simple and Direct: Correspondence, 1977-86 (Box 320)
    - Simple and Direct: Comments and reviews, 1975-76 (Box 320)
    - Simple and Direct: Galleys, misc., 1975-76 (Box 320)
    - Simple and Direct: Publicity and mailing, 1975-76 (Box 320)
    - Simple and Direct, Revised edition, 1983-85 (Box 320)
    - A Stroll With William James: Correspondence, 1976-86 (Box 321)
    - A Stroll With William James: Comments on the book, 1983-86 (Box 321)
    - A Stroll With William James: Excerpts and comments on excerpts, 1980-83 (Box 321)
    - A Stroll With William James: Reviews (1), 1983-86 (Box 321)
    - A Stroll With William James: Reviews (2), 1983-86 (Box 321)
    - A Stroll With William James: University of Chicago Press Edition, 1982-86 (Box 321)
    - Teacher in America, 1970-86 (Box 322)
    - The Tyranny of Art, 1972-82 (Box 322)
    - The Use and Abuse of Art: Correspondence and reviews, 1974-84 (Box 322)
  - C. Books: With contributions by Barzun:
    - Flaubert, 1962-67 (Box 322)
    - Orphéide by H. M. Barzun, 1979-81 (Box 322)
    - The Political Volumes of the Collected Works Walter Bagehot, 1965-75 (Box 322)
    - The Written Word (collection of essays) 1969-72 (Box 322)
  - D. Books: Edited by Barzun:
    - Modern American Usage by Wilson Follett, 1965-80 (Box 322)
    - The Selected Writings of John Jay Chapman, 1957-80 (Box 322)
  - E. Books: Translations by Barzun:
    - BeauMarchais:Figaro's Marriage: Correspondence, galleys, misc., 1961-79 (Box 323)
    - Diderot:Rameau's Nephew, 1958-75 (Box 323)
    - Diderot:Selected Prose, 1962-71 (Box 323)
    - Flaubert:Dictionary, 1959-77 (Box 323)
    - French Plays: Galleys and typescripts 1938-56 (Box 323)
  - Address card files, 1975-86 (Box 324)
  - Appointment calendars, 1975-86 (Box 324)
  - Wendell H. Taylor Files, 1929-1986
    - Wendell H. Taylor: Correspondence, n.d.; 1936 1972-85 (Box 325)
    - A Catalog of Crime, 1975-85 (Box 326)
    - Classics of 20th Century Crime, 1980-84 (Box 326)
    - History of Science (course taught by WHT), 1929-50 (Box 326)
    - WHT's comments on JB's books, 1956-68 (Box 326)
    - WHT's family tree, 1980 (Box 326)
    - WHT's will and related correspondence, 1976 (Box 326)
    - Obituaries for WHT, correspondence and related materials, 1985-86 (Box 326)
    - WHT Prize at Lawrenceville School, 1985-86 (Box 326)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 326)
    - Photographs of WHT; samples of his bookplate and Signature, 1922-56 (Box 326)
    - Wendell H. Taylor: Printed materials (Box 327)
    - Pamphlets by WHT and magazines with his contributions (high school magazines), 1922 1933 (Box 327)
    - Books by WHT (Box 327)
    - Books from WHT's library (Box 327)
  - Printed Materials:
    - Books with references to JB (Box 328)
    - Books by JB (Box 328)
    - Books by JB (Box 329)
    - Books about JB (Box 329)
    - Articles and Pamphlets by JB (Box 330)
    - Books translated by JB (Box 331)
    - Books with contributions by JB (Box 332)
    - Books with contributions by JB (Box 333)
    - Books with contributions by JB (Box 334)
    - Books inscribed to JB (Box 335)
    - Books inscribed to JB (Box 336)
    - Books inscribed to JB (Box 337)
    - Books inscribed to JB (Box 338)
    - Books inscribed to JB (Box 339)
    - Books from JB's library (Box 340)
    - Books from JB's library, some with annotations (Box 341)
    - Books from JB’s library, some with annotations (Box 342)
- Series XIV: 1988 Gift
  - Articles edited by Barzun, undated (Box 343)
  - A Catalogue of Crime: Files:
    - Pamphlets, 1975-81 (Box 343)
    - Photocopies and related materials, 1968-86 (Box 343)
    - Short Stories, 1963-73 (Box 343)
  - Cosmopolitan Club: Programs and related materials, 1958-73 (Box 343)
  - "Doctors Afield": Article by Barzun, 1971 (Box 343)
  - From Parnassus (book of essays about Barzun): Correspondence and related materials, 1983-84 (Box 343)
  - Morgan, Paul: Oh Clerihew!: Page proofs, undated (Box 343)
  - Mysteries: Articles, catalogues, and related materials 1965-84 (Box 343)
  - Scribner's Editorial Files:
    - Hemingway, Ernest:The Dangerous Summer, 1984 (Box 343)
  - Simple and Direct (revised edition):
    - Files (Box 344)
    - Correspondence, corrected drafts, and related materials (Box 344)
    - Corrected manuscript with notes (Box 344)
    - Research materials (Box 344)
  - The Use and Abuse of Art: "Speaking Copy" from Mellon Lectures (Box 344)
  - Books with contributions by JB (Box 345)
  - Correspondence with authors (arranged), 1986-1987 (Box 346)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1987 (Box 346)
  - Columbia University, 1972-1987 (Box 346)
  - Crime fiction:
    - Articles by leading practitioners and a few others, 1951-1987 (Box 347)
    - Brief reviews by Barzun and Wendell Taylor, 1960-1982 (Box 347)
    - Correspondence (arranged), 1983-1988 (Box 347)
    - Important articles, reviews and documents on critical and popular taste, 1983-1988, (2 folders) (Box 347)
    - Interesting promotion and other fugitives, 1950s-1986 (Box 348)
    - Reviews, printed and autograph, 1974-1985 (Box 348)
    - Stories and articles, 1954-1987 (Box 348)
    - Writings on, by Taylor and Barzun, 1950s-1985 (Box 348)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica. Comments and rewriting by Barzun, 1981-1983 (Box 349)
  - Honors (Box 349)
  - Lectures accepted, 1984-1986 (Box 349)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 349)
  - A Word or Two Before You Go. Correspondence through 1986 (Box 349)
  - Photographs (Box 349)
  - Manuscripts, 1986-1981
    - Roberts, David Lindsay "Bohr, Trollope, Acoustics and the Island of Long Island" (Box 350)
    - Tolstoy: The Ultimate Reconciliation by Martine de Courcel. photocopy of proof, (4 folders) (Box 350)
    - A Word or Two Before You Go ..., author's set (Box 350)
  - Books and offprints inscribed to and collected by Barzun (Box 351-354)
  - Oversized Material:
    - Four of Barzun's diplomas from Columbia University (1 tube) (Mapcase 14-13-7)
    - Several honorary certificates including one Barzun's nomination to the Ordre National de la Legion d'Honneur, (1 folder) (Mapcase 14-13-7)
- Series XV: 1989 Gift
  - Correspondence:
    - About Berlioz, 1957-88, (3 folders) (Box 355)
    - About writings, 1985-88, (3 folders) (Box 355)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1986-88 (Box 355)
    - By or about Herbert Jacobson, Lionel and others, 1986-89 (Box 356)
    - Catalogue of Crime, 1986-88 (Box 356)
    - Columbia University, 1987-88 (Box 356)
    - Council for Basic Education, 1986-88 (Box 356)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1988, (2 folders) (Box 356)
    - General, 1987-89 (Box 356)
    - Lectures, 1982-87, (2 folders) (Box 357)
    - Lectures and articles, 1986-88 (Box 357)
    - Recommendations, 1984-88 (Box 357)
    - Tolstoy: The Ultimate Reconciliation, 1983-89, (2 folders) (Box 357)
    - U.S. English, 1985-88 (Box 357)
    - Correspondence with Charles Miller concerning his Auden: An American Friendship, 1981-1987 (Box 358)
    - Correspondence with James Trefil, 1979-88 (Box 358)
    - Correspondence with publishers, 1986-88, (2 folders) (Box 358)
    - Correspondence with William Krsner and a synopsis of a proposed novel, 1982-88 (Box 358)
    - Correspondence with writers, 1987-88, (3 folders) (Box 358)
    - A Word or Two Before You Go ..., 1987-88 (Box 358)
  - Documents: Book dealer invoices, 1976-85 (Box 358)
  - Articles by Barzun A --Z, 1986-89 (Box 359)
  - Lectures by Barzun chronological, 1986-87 (Box 360)
  - Crime Fiction, 1952-89:
    - Arrangements, invitations and publicity (Box 361)
    - Articles, published and unpublished (Box 361)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 361)
    - Notes, letters, reports on Catalogue of Crime and Fifty Classics of Crime (Box 361)
  - One correspondence file box of personal correspondence and documents shelved with the other restricted unnumbered containers.
    [Closed until 2047 ]
- Series XVI: 1990 Gift
  - Correspondence, Editorial and Personal (1986-1988):
    - A (Box 362)
    - B (Box 362)
    - Bentley, Joanne (Box 362)
    - Bertin, Michael (Box 362)
    - Bloom, Peter (Box 362)
    - C (Box 362)
    - Cournand, Marie-Claire (Box 362)
    - The Culture We Deserve (I) (Box 362)
    - The Culture We Deserve (II) (Box 362)
    - Cstcsery-Ronay, Elizabeth (Box 362)
    - Davenport, William (Box 362)
    - E (Box 363)
    - F (Box 363)
    - Feinstein. Herbert (Box 363)
    - G (Box 363)
    - Goodman, Jonathan (Box 363)
    - Ha-He (Box 363)
    - Hf-Hz (Box 363)
    - I & J (Box 363)
    - K (Box 363)
    - L (Box 363)
    - M (Box 363)
    - McAleer, John (Box 363)
    - Miller, Charles (Box 363)
    - N (Box 363)
    - P (Box 364)
    - R (Box 364)
    - Reeve, Katherine (Box 364)
    - Sa-Sm (Box 364)
    - Sn-Sz (Box 364)
    - T & U (Box 364)
    - V (Box 364)
    - W (Box 364)
    - Wadsworth, Robert (Box 364)
    - Y & Z (Box 364)
    - Unidentified (Box 364)
    - By First Name (Box 364)
    - Miscellaneous to Publishers (Box 364)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Materials (Box 364)
  - Typescripts and Proofs:
    - Typescripts and Proofs-Pre-1986 (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-1986(1) (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-1896(2) (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-1987 (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-1988(1) (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-1988(11) (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-1989 (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-Undated(I) (Box 365)
    - Typescripts and Proofs-Undated(II) (Box 365)
  - Subject Folders:
    - Tolstoy (I) (Box 366)
    - Tolstoy (II) (Box 366)
    - Depot. No. 500 (Box 366)
    - Lucy Poate Stebbins (I) (Box 366)
    - Lucy Poate Stebbins (II) (Box 366)
  - Books with Annotations (Box 366)
  - Books Inscribed to J. Barzun (Box 367)
- Series XVII: 1991 Gift
  - Correspondence:
    - Advice to Authors, 1989-90(1) (Box 368)
    - Advice to Authors, 1989-90(2) (Box 368)
    - Advice to Authors, 1989-90(3) (Box 368)
    - Articles Accepted, 1985-91 (Box 368)
    - Berlioz and Other Music, 1983-88 (Box 368)
    - Berlioz and Other Music, 1989-90 (Box 368)
    - Comments on Writings by Barzun, 1989-90 (Box 368)
    - Lectures Accepted and Lectures Declined, 1988-90 (Box 368)